et397 [at] cornell.edu https://emtseng.me

Emily Tseng

Research Interests

I study (a) how data-driven technology facilitates novel harms to safety, privacy, health and well-being; and (b) how technology designers can enable consentful and participatory interventions with impacted communities. My work builds from *human-computer interaction* and *computational social science* to design, build, and deploy sociotechnical systems in real-world contexts, towards improving conditions for people marginalized within society. In my PhD, I have worked specifically on privacy for survivors of intimate partner violence, worker-centered design for home care aides, and workplace surveillance and mental health.

Education

2010-14

2019-now	Ph.D. at Cornell University, Department of Information Science
	Committee: Nicola Dell (chair), Deborah Estrin, Tom Ristenpart, Karen Levy.

2017-19	M.S. at Cornell Tech, Information Science - Health Tech	GPA: 3.9/4.0
	Relevant coursework: Applied Machine Learning, Deep Learning, Natural Lar	
	Processing, Human-Computer Interaction, Interactive Device Design.	
	Advised by Nicola Dell and Deborah Estrin.	

B.A. at Princeton University, *Ecology & Evolutionary Biology (EEB)* GPA: 3.5/4.0 Concentration in Global Health and Health Policy. Studied epidemiology, data journalism and social policy, with a focus on computational modeling of infectious disease epidemics. Advised by Bryan Grenfell and Tiffany Bogich.

Awards & Honors

wai us & i	1011013
2022	Rising Stars in EECS
2022	Best Paper Award, ACM CHI
2021	Microsoft Research PhD Fellowship
2021	Digital Life Initiative Doctoral Fellowship
2020	Best Paper Award, ACM CSCW
2020	Distinguished Paper Award, USENIX Security Symposium
2020	Internet Defense Prize (third place), USENIX Security Symposium
2020	CRA-WP Grad Cohort for Women (postponed due to COVID-19, attended in 2021)
2019	Best Paper Honorable Mention, ACM CSCW
2019	Advocate of New York City Award, Mayor's Office to End Domestic & Gender-Based Violence
2019	Cornell University Information Science Department Fellowship
	First-year fellowship awarded for exceptional preparation & promise (top 1.5% of applicants).
2017	Cornell Tech merit scholarship for Master's-level study
2014	Top Senior Thesis in Mathematical Modeling, Princeton EEB
2014	Society of Sigma Xi (scientific research honor society), Princeton University

Refereed Conference and Journal Publications

- * indicates equal contribution, listed in alphabetical order by last name.
 - 1. Dinh A, **Tseng E**, Yin AL, Estrin D, Greenwald P, Fortenko A. 2023. *Perceptions of Augmented Reality in Remote Medical Care: Interview Study of Emergency Telemedicine Providers*. JMIR Formative Research 2023;7:e45211. pdf. online.
 - 2. Adler, D.*, **Tseng**, E.*, Moon, K.C., Young, J.Q., Kane, J.M., Moss, E., Mohr, D.C., and Choudhury, T. 2022. Burnout and the Quantified Workplace: Tensions around Personal Sensing Interventions for Stress in Resident Physicians. Proc. ACM Hum.-Comput. Interact., CSCW (Nov. 2022). pdf. online.
 - 3. Ming, J., Kuo, E.F., Go, K., **Tseng, E.**, Kallas, J., Vashistha, A., Sterling, M., and Dell, N. "I Go Beyond and Beyond": Examining the Invisible Work of Home Health Aides. Proc. ACM Hum.-Comput. Interact. 7, CSCW1, Article 59 (April 2023). pdf. online.
 - Tseng, E., Sabet, M., Bellini, R., Sodhi, H., Ristenpart, T., and Dell, N. 2022. Care Infrastructures for Digital Privacy and Security in Intimate Partner Violence. In Proc. ACM Conf. on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '22). pdf. online. video.
 Best Paper Award.
 - 5. Chen, J.X.*, McDonald, A.*, Zou, Y.*, **Tseng, E.,** Roundy, K.A., Tamersoy, A., Schaub, F., Ristenpart, T., and Dell, N. 2022. *Trauma-Informed Computing: Towards Safer Technology Experiences for All.* In Proc. ACM Conf. on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '22). pdf. online.
 - 6. **Tseng, E.**, Freed, D., Engel, K., Ristenpart, T., and Dell, N. 2021. *A Digital Safety Dilemma: Analysis of Computer-Mediated Computer Security Interventions for Intimate Partner Violence During COVID-19.* In Proc. ACM Conf. on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '21). pdf. online. video.
 - 7. Bellini, R., **Tseng, E.,** McDonald, N., Greenstadt, R., McCoy, D., Ristenpart, T. and Dell, N. "So-called privacy breeds evil": Narrative Justifications for Intimate Partner Surveillance in Online Forums. Proc. ACM Hum.-Comput. Interact., Issue CSCW. 2020. pdf.

 Best Paper Award.
 - 8. **Tseng, E.**, Bellini, R., McDonald, N., Danos, M., Greenstadt, R., McCoy, D., Dell, N. and Ristenpart, T. 2020. The Tools and Tactics Used in Intimate Partner Surveillance: An Analysis of Online Infidelity Forums. 29th USENIX Security Symposium. pdf. online.

 Distinguished Paper Award and Internet Defense Prize, third place.
 - 9. Sterling, MR, **Tseng**, **E**, Poon, A, Cho, J, Avgar, AC, Kern, LM, Ankuda, CK, Dell, N. 2020. Experiences of Home Health Care Workers in New York City During the Coronavirus Disease 2019 Pandemic: A Qualitative Analysis. JAMA Internal Medicine. pdf. online.
 - 10. **Tseng, E.,** Okeke, F., Sterling, M., and Dell, N. 2020. "We can learn. Why not?": Designing Technologies to Engender Equity for Home Health Aides. In Proc. ACM Conf. on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI '20). pdf. online.

- 11. Sterling, M. R., Dell, N., Piantella, B., Cho, J., Kaur, H., **Tseng, E.,** Okeke, F., Brown, M., Leung, P. B. K., Silva, A. F., Shaw, A. L., Kern, L. M. 2020. *Understanding the Workflow of Home Healthcare for Patients with Heart Failure*. Journal of General Internal Medicine. pdf. online.
- 12. Freed, D.*, Havron, S.*, **Tseng, E.**, Gallardo A., Chatterjee, R., Ristenpart, T., and Dell, N.. 2019. "Is my phone hacked?" Analyzing Clinical Computer Security Interventions with Survivors of Intimate Partner Violence. Proc. ACM Hum.-Comput. Interact.: Vol. 3, Issue CSCW, Article 202. <u>pdf</u>. <u>online</u>. Best Paper Honorable Mention.
- 13. Okeke, F., **Tseng, E.,** Piantella, B., Brown, M., Kaur, H., Sterling, M., and Dell, N. 2019. *Technology, Home Health Care, and Heart Failure: A Qualitative Analysis with Multiple Stakeholders.* ACM SIGCAS Conference on Computing & Sustainable Societies (COMPASS 2019). <u>pdf. online</u>.

Teaching and Advising

Cornell University, Ithaca, NY (hybrid due to COVID-19)

Teaching Assistant, Summer School on Designing Technology for Social Impact

Teaching Assistant, CS 1340 / INFO 1260: Choices and Consequences in Computing,

Profs. Jon Kleinberg and Karen Levy

Summer 2021

Spring 2021

Cornell Tech, New York, NY

Teaching Assistant, INFO 5375: Machine Learning in Health, Prof. Fei Wang	Spring 2023
Guest Lecturer, CS / INFO 5600: AI & Healthcare, Prof. Rajalakshmi Nandakumar	Fall 2021
Teaching Assistant, CS 5682 / INFO 6410: HCI & Design, Prof. Nicola Dell	Fall 2020
Research Internship Supervisor, Technion + Cornell Tech Intern Program	Fall 2019
Grader, CS 5740: Natural Language Processing, Prof. Yoav Artzi	Spring 2019
Lead Teaching Assistant, Product Studio, Prof. Deborah Estrin	Fall 2018

Weill Cornell Medical College, New York, NY

Guest Lecturer, HCPL 8101: Digital Health, Prof. Deborah Estrin Summer 2020

Fullstack Academy, New York, NY

Software Engineering Teaching Fellow

Summer 2017

- Taught and mentored 80+ students at a selective software engineering bootcamp.
- Delivered 10-minute talk on inclusive design and web accessibility [video]

Presentations

Invited Talks

2022 University of Chicago, People and Technology Seminar

AnitaB.org Grace Hopper Celebration, Research Showcase

Google, Trust & Safety Research Speaker Series

Microsoft Research, Project Green Workshop: Community-Driven Innovation & Health Equity Stanford University, HCI Seminar

2021 Microsoft Research, PhD Fellowship Showcase

Cornell Tech, Digital Life Initiative Seminar

MIT Visualization Group

CUNY School of Law, Students Against Cyber Sexual Abuse

2020 United Hospital Fund/Greater New York Hospital Association Annual Symposium

MIT CSAIL Security Seminar

Facebook Research

Cornell Tech, Precision Behavioral Health Initiative

Conference and Workshop Presentations

2023, Privacy Law Scholars Conference, selected for presentation

2022, Joel R. Reidenberg Northeast Privacy Scholars Workshop, selected for lightning session

2022, Care Infrastructures for Digital Security and Privacy in IPV, ACM CHI [video]

2021, A Digital Safety Dilemma, ACM CHI [video]

2020, The Tools and Tactics of Intimate Partner Violence, USENIX Security Symposium [video]

Academic and University Service

2022-23, Cornell Information Science PhD Student Mentoring Program, Organizer

2021-22, Diversity, Equity and Inclusion Strategic Committee at Cornell Tech, PhD Representative

2021-22, Faculty Hiring Committee at Cornell Tech, PhD Coordinator

2021, ACM CHI, Student Volunteer (fully remote conference)

2020, PhDs at Cornell Tech, Co-President

Workshop and Panel Participation

2023, ACM FAccT, Community-Collaborative Visions for Computing Research, Organizer.

2022, Data & Society, Care + Tech Convening. Discussant.

2022, Human-Computer Interaction Consortium. Student Participant.

2022, Data & Society, The Social Life of Algorithmic Harms. Discussant.

2021, ACM CSCW, Subtle CSCW Traits: Tensions Around Identity Formation and Online Activism in the Asian Diaspora, Organizer. [proposal]

Program Committee Membership

2023, ACM Designing Interactive Systems (DIS) – Associate Chair, Critical Computing, Design Theory, and Change through Design Subcommittee.

Reviewing

ACM Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI)

Special Recognition for Outstanding Reviews, 2022, 2023

ACM Computer Supported Cooperative Work and Social Computing (CSCW)

Special Recognition for Outstanding Reviews, 2021, 2022

ACM Transactions on Human-Computer Interaction (TOCHI)

ACM Fairness, Accountability, and Transparency (FAccT)

USENIX Symposium on Usable Privacy and Security (SOUPS)

Usable Security and Privacy (USEC) Symposium, co-located with the Internet Society's Network and Distributed System Security (NDSS) Symposium

HEALTHI Workshop on Healthy Interfaces, co-located with ACM Intelligent User Interfaces (IUI)

AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM)

Past Research

Extracting family history from unstructured clinical notes

- Developed a model (LSTM-CRF) extracting family history from unstructured text in patient forms.
- Awarded student travel grant to present at the OHNLP/BioCreativ workshop at ACM-BCB 2018.

Evaluating the usability of a personal data filtering interface

PI: Deborah Estrin, Ph.D. (Cornell Tech)

- Usability study of an interface for filtering sensitive data from a Google Takeout.

Modeling the dynamics of enterovirus-71 in Taiwan: An application of the TSIR model PI: Bryan Grenfell, Ph.D. (Princeton University)

- Developed a time-series model of the impact of vaccination on EV-71 infection rates in Taiwan.
- Awarded departmental prize for excellence in mathematical modeling [poster].

Relevant Industry Experience

Microsoft Research, remote due to COVID-19

Spring and Summer 2022

Research Intern

- Mentored by Mary L. Gray within the Social Media Collective.

Pfizer, Inc., New York, NY

Summer Associate Summer 2018

- Led a team of UX researchers and technologists to synthesize user stories, product requirements and storyboards for a care navigation product addressing health disparities within the Welsh NHS.
- Interviewed domain experts on the feasibility of a consumer voice product for patient support.

Biomeme, Inc., Philadelphia, PA

Product & Business Development Associate

2014 - 2016

- Developed an at-home sexual health diagnostic for a national reproductive healthcare provider.
- Piloted a point-of-care influenza diagnostic with a clinic network in Nairobi, Kenya.
- Conducted UX studies to guide development of a consumer-facing tool for personal DNA analysis.

The Daily Princetonian, Princeton, NJ

Managing Editor

2013 - 2014

- Led 100+ staff of a collegiate news organization publishing in print 5x/week and online 24/7.
- Built web and data journalism departments, and expanded the paper's multimedia capabilities.

Oxford University Clinical Research Unit (OUCRU), Ho Chi Minh City, Vietnam

Research Intern

Summer 2013

- Conducted literature reviews, performed data analyses (R) and mapped patient enrollment (GIS, Illustrator) for ongoing clinical studies at a tertiary tuberculosis hospital.
- Funded by the Gates Foundation Global Health Grand Challenge.

Doctors Without Borders / Medecins Sans Frontieres (MSF), New York, NY

Editorial & Multimedia Intern

Summer 2011, 2012

- Produced audio, video & web features on MSF field staff at humanitarian aid sites worldwide.